Welcome back to Critical Path. I am
joined today with my co-host Dalibor
Petrovic and Daniel Keefer. Gentlemen,
as always, it is a pleasure to speak
with you on our Friday afternoon at the
time of recording. Um real quick, uh
today we're talking about executive
adoption because this is one of the
primary things that some people still
get wrong and we're seeing evidence of
it out there. Um and this is actually
kind of our forte is
the the number one signal of success or
predictor of success for generative AI
adoption is executive oversight, which
means starting at the highest possible
level, whether it's the CEO, the owner,
the founder, whatever it happens to be.
And the second biggest predictor is
management engagement. And so that's a
big part of what we focus on um with our
clients uh between the three of us uh
individually and collectively. So, uh
guys, what are what are we seeing out
there? Um I I guess I'll I'll kick off
with a subtopic that Dalibor and I were
talking about just before we hit record,
which is um there's often an an
activation point uh where where a an
executive or a CEO, you know, there's
kind of a lag between they know that AI
is a thing and then there's confusion
and that sort of thing. So, Dalibor, can
you uh can you repeat what you said
earlier cuz it was it was spot-on.
>> So, to me,
uh it is now after after doing this for
a while, it is clear that the the best
way to approach the organizational
transformation into this world of AI and
intelligent automation is actually
top-down. It's actually top-down. It's
to get to get the most senior, most
accountable leader
to personally see and experience
this wow moment of engaging with
frontier intelligence in a safe,
coordinated, proper manner.
And that that to me is the gateway drug
that then gets
ultimately the whole organization over
over the bridge over the Rubicon in in
in in into into what ultimately then
becomes, you know, ignited fire around
cascading intelligence throughout the
enterprise.
So, it it is absolutely top-down
and and my personal advice is that uh
everyone who is championing
intelligence and automation within an
enterprise
ought to objectively and honestly assess
to what degree do those executives at
the very top
personally understand and personally use
this technology.
>> Yeah. Daniel?
>> Yeah, I mean the interesting thing here
is we're seeing the exact same pattern
as with digital transformation.
Uh it starts too low in in the
organization, right? And then after uh
a time where where companies can see
that they're not achieving the desired
return on investment. But then they
start looking at like
how can we do this differently, right?
And and this is also what I see when
when working with with companies.
They're starting to understand that
C-level needs to be involved just like
uh Daniel Ball says. Um
And first of all, this is not like a
technology transformation task. It's
actually a people transformation task.
And it's just it's a strategic task,
which is why it's logical it needs to
start at at the top.
>> This This reminds me of like there's
many many dimensions to unpack, but I
think I think the primary thing is
uh you know, one thing that we're seeing
out there is that some sometimes leaders
at various levels, they do kind of want
to just think it as a of it as a like a
vendor issue. Like which piece of
software do we buy?
How do we vet the piece of software? And
then, you know, what are the security
and and integration and compliance
risks? And and certainly, you know,
we've talked about this before how
at one level, yeah, AI is just another
piece of of software.
You know, if you had to explain it, it's
a it's a kind of SaaS. Right now, it's
often delivered as a SaaS. You can
do it on prem. You can put it on your
own infrastructure.
But, and this is something that I think
uh a many, many leaders have not yet
been activated on. And when I say
leaders, I mean, you know, C-suite and
above.
They know that AI is big and important.
They hear it and they know that it's
important, but it's usually just kind of
a top-down edict of saying, "Okay,
everyone needs to be AI competent." Um
but they don't use it themselves or they
don't realize how big it is. And there's
I think there's probably several levels
of activation now that I say it out loud
where there's the initial one where, you
know, a leader goes from skeptical to,
you know, confused and enthusiastic but
but eager. And then they realize
actually this is going to rewire the
whole organization. And Daniel, to your
point, that, you know, the what the
Boston Consulting Group and everyone
else has settled on is the 10-20-70
rule, which is that it's 10% you know,
the actual tool, 20% data and
infrastructure, and then 70% people. And
I that maybe maybe that's a something to
to double click on for a while is just
really emphasizing what does it mean
when we talk about how the generative AI
transformation is 70% people and culture
and processes.
E- Either either
either one of you guys, what do you want
to jump in and add to that?
>> Yeah, I would say, I mean,
this is a total redesign of the company
you need to make, right? And that cannot
be done without the CEO. So, it needs to
be some form of combination
across the C-suite and and the CEO. And
then,
uh people need to realize this is about
setting a strategy first, right? And the
last decision and least important are
the tool decisions.
And most companies are doing it in
reverse. They're picking somebody minus
one minus two below C level to
to take
tool decisions at this point, which is
now why there's no real return on
investment on nine out of 10 AI
projects.
>> Yeah.
>> And what I would what I would add is
that uh
the real change in leadership here
happens when
the most senior person in charge
understands
that we are not talking about tools here
as in playing solutions, but we are
talking about an agent and agentic
co-
co-piloting through a sense.
And when they start seeing that the
potential of transformation that goes
beyond simply deploying a
technology and
approaching it like it's a it's a single
tech improvement project of the past.
So, to me there is a big difference
in
most senior leaders personally
experiencing the power of engaging with
a frontier model
to experience what it feels like when
you are
borrowing additional IQ or orchestrating
teams of intelligence performing tasks
on your behalf helping you
trigger your creativity and curiosity
personally and having that experience
and just hearing about it or reading
about it in the newspaper on flights and
then delegating it to your IT leader
and expecting the organization to
generate exceptional value in a short
period of time. That's the the bridge I
think that we are talking about
crossing.
And what I've learned is that there is
actually no other way to do this
than to spend some dedicated time
one-on-one with those senior executives
and taking them gradually through this
process of
personal discovery
in a way that will be clear and and gain
them confidence.
>> Yeah.
>> And that really I think is the recipe of
how to how to how to properly approach,
how to where to start
when you talk about this transformation.
>> I remember earlier this year Dalibor
when I Claude Bot came out. You actually
spent a weekend learning it cuz you said
this is really important and you had
your own Claude Bot set up and
you know and and this is this is
something that I I am even myself guilty
of is being a tech guy, being at the
frontier, I can get lazy and complacent
and I you know I'm I'm resistant to use
some of the new tools.
But I think that that is building an
intuition for what these things can and
cannot do at a personal level is
indispensable for everyone at every
level of the organization. This is
something that uh you know last week we
had I read a comment from from one of my
fans where the the the you know their
CTO or CIO wanted to you know get back
into coding and and code up a you know
convert an app to prove that he didn't
need it you know as big of a a software
development team. I'm like that is a
great idea. You absolutely 100% should
test yourself so that you know what
these things can and cannot do. And that
also reminds me of some of the stuff
that I've gotten from the from the
surveys that I've sent out which is that
there is still a very very wide
disparity between the so-called frontier
models. Uh Gemini being one of the
laggards in terms of usefulness. And
this this actually is is a big barrier
to adoption in some organizations where
it's like well we're a Google partner
and Google Gemini you know our Google
sales reps told us that it's it's the
best and it's good enough and then
you know, plenty of people are like,
"Yeah, whatever." They use Claude Coder
or or ChatGPT Codex,
uh personally, and then they just merge
the code in somewhere else. And of
course, coding is just one particular
area. There's terminal use, there are uh
there's research purposes, there's the
aesthetic component, you know, using
these things for generating white papers
or generating slide decks or that sort
of stuff. So, there's there's there's a
very very what's called a jagged
frontier. So, there are things where
even within one family of AIs, they're
they can excel dramatically at certain
things and be terrible at other things,
but also between AI families or between
AI companies, there can be dramatic
disparities in terms of capability, user
experience, consistency. This is one of
the biggest reasons why people have
still not really uh adopted Grok that
much is just because it is a wildly
inconsistent model. Um so, yeah, just
just adding some some layers to think
about in terms of
>> Yeah.
>> you know, okay, yeah, you know, a friend
of mine used uh used ChatGPT once a year
or two ago and concluded that it can't
code. Well, okay, you know, that's you
know, that that's prehistoric by today's
standards.
>> Yeah.
Well, you know, what I would invite
people to think about is we are actually
now at the point
where accessing frontier model genuinely
helps those leaders perform as if they
had a whole team with them at individual
level.
And it it genuinely can feel like you
are a smarter leader with surrounded
with this frontier intelligence. And it
gets better and better all the time. So,
now if you think about this, if if you
approach this methodically and help
[clears throat] top-down your leadership
uh learn at learn, organize, adopt, and
use. I'm not necessarily even talking
about deep integration with customer
data. And not not that, just expanding
everyone's personal frontier of
creativity, performance, capability,
capacity, adaptability,
you are actually going to come up with a
true smarter enterprise. We were talking
about business intelligence for decades.
We are now at at the moment where you
can actually have a more intelligent
enter enterprise by adding intelligence,
quote unquote, on top of the
intelligence of all of your leaders and
team members. It's a phenomenal moment.
I would invite people to start thinking
at from it from that perspective, as
well as the perspective of your of
course we need to deploy it into the
process to automate ourselves and all
that good stuff.
And this starts
with executive
fluency.
>> Yeah, and I still don't think most
C-suite leaders have actually
experienced this themselves. I mean,
it's a little bit
It's a little bit like when you go into
to
executive meeting, right? If one person
has prepared for the meeting a whole
week, 80 hours, and the rest have not
prepared. I mean, that is the difference
between between using these frontier
models and amplifying yourself the right
way. So, I think what we'll start to see
is the A team of executives and the B
team, right?
And when the A team
>> [clears throat]
>> comes into these meetings, you know, the
CEO will notice the difference
immediately.
And you can simply just not afford to be
on the B team. The B team are the
unamplified
leaders.
>> Yeah, you're actually What a What a
great observation, Daniel.
The unamplified leaders. That That's
exactly what I'm speaking of. I love the
term. And And that happens when you
properly use the frontier models
uh and you're staying ahead
uh I asked the are ahead of the game. I
I love that. I love I love that. You're
right, 100%.
>> So, all right. Let's Let's imagine that
we've got, you know, uh CEO or owner
founder in front of us
who said, "Okay, guys. I'm convinced,
you know, I'm starting to use Claude.
I'm starting to use ChatGPT. It's
powerful. This is something that we've
we've talked about uh repeatedly
offline, mentioned it last week, which
is there is a very very large chasm
between
great, you know, the C-suite is using
it, upper management is using it, most
of management is using it, and getting
to the rest of the organization. So,
um what's what's what's the next thing
that they do? And And so far in our
observation, one of the most effective
next steps is once you get the once you
get the upper leadership fully fully on
board, the very next thing that you do
is you get um all of leadership team on
board, and you build either a
transformation team or a steering team
or, you know, some some that that
A-team, that squad who's responsible for
driving the transformation. So, how do
those conversations usually go um in in
in your experience, guys?
>> Yeah, I think that the most important
question is, what do you want to
achieve, right? And that will be
different uh from uh from company to
company and leaders who lead it, right?
So, if you are in a growth sector, you
want to use AI to grow. And I think uh
one of the the sessions I love to do is
say, "Okay, if you could triple your
head count, what would you do?"
And then after you you do this, you say,
"Okay, you can't triple the head count,
but how can we do this with AI?"
Or the other way around saying, "Okay,
the company is a cash cow. It will be
very difficult to grow. Okay, how can we
do what we're doing today with less
people?" Obviously, the the
the latter one is not nearly as fun
because it's about cost cutting. Uh but
I think both will result in a much
higher profit. And and I think, you
know, that that is what companies are
are set in the world to do, right? It's
It is basically to make money and of
course hire people and create growth in
the economy. So, I think this is where
you need to start. If you don't know
what you want to achieve, you know, you
can't really make a plan.
>> Yeah. So,
interesting. I just [clears throat] want
to reflect on that briefly is uh you
know, it's it's not just AI is the thing
that we need to adopt and transform the
the company. You're saying it it the the
first question is actually starting even
further back, which is what what is this
company's phase of life even? Are we in
growth? Are we in maintenance? Do we
need to Do we actually need to transform
or pivot it to a new uh business model?
And that's actually where the
conversation starts. Sorry, Dalipor. Go
ahead.
>> I was going to say this is exactly why
we are referring to what we are doing is
helping organizations
become
become their best versions in the age of
intelligence and automation. So, So,
this is
less about do we have an AI strategy? I
think that's a wrong question to ask. Do
we have an AI strategy? Maybe not even
wrong question. Too easy of a question.
The right question is do we have a
strategy
for the age of intelligence and the age
of automation?
And that question then drives the the
right conversation, Daniel, that that
Daniel talks about.
Um
So, and the beautiful part is that we
have, you know, we we we understand um
the model and we understand all the
pieces of the model that an organization
will need to consider in order to
succeed in this transformation, right?
From the fact that it started, as we
discussed already, with leadership
and that in that leadership there is an
aspect of the strategy answering that
question. Like, what is our strategy?
Who Who are we
in this moment of of of of rise of the
machines and intelligence?
The component on fluency, the component
on governance and risk
that
typically becomes one of the earlier
conversations coming straight out or
even within as part of the strategy
conversations.
And then the capacity to to transform
itself, the organizational capacity to
transform itself. And to me
those are the aspects that all of the
leaders need to understand, own,
and then have some support and guidance
to actually advance.
And this is where this is where
this is where this bumped-up ambition or
or eyes wide open
convert into actionable
strategy and then transformation.
And by the way, in my experience, that
strategy if if the organization is
serious about this,
what will typically happen is that this
conversation about strategy that
translates into, you know, let's now do
something about it, develop a strategic
plan, typically then that translates
into, okay, so what do we actually do
next,
which then triggers the conversation
about ours as putting together the
actual transformation program of work
and organizing our program around our
aspirations and priorities. Where, for
example, what I would typically see in a
program transformation program like that
in today's day and age is consistent
ambition, what do we do about growth, as
growth stream of the strategy, at the
same time, what do we do about our
optimization, the optimization stream of
the strategy. So, those those two are
typically what we see fronting it,
enabled by sort of four back-up streams
or enablement streams, one focusing on
data, another one focusing on
technology, another one, of course,
focusing on people, and typically one
focusing on building internal
capabilities
to continuously convert ideas into
intelligent automation results. And that
to me feels like the structure.
The the I'm now typically ob- some
variant of that structure is what I'm
observing across multiple different
clients I'm working with.
>> Excellent.
What differentiates
uh A-team players, executives, and
leaders
uh and and senior management from
B-team? [clears throat]
>> I think it's simply getting into AI
themselves, right? I think curiosity is
super important. And then understanding
that it it's it's a context and data
game, not uh about who has the best
tool. Um
I still see very few leaders
understanding AI amplification and what
it really is. And I try to build the
mental picture for them that imagine
you're you have this huge exoskeleton
like you're you know, going to your own
robot, right? And you you have to fight
with the competitors. Imagine one person
has the exoskeleton on and the other one
does not, right? It's going to be a
super short fight. A very very unfair
one, right?
>> going to say that's that's sounds like a
a very stacked deck. But that but you're
right, that's how it feels. If you if
you do have, you know, the the
superpower, if you have the jetpack on
versus if you don't, your fit your your
your operating at a at a disability or
or you know, uh supreme disadvantage.
Sorry, I
go ahead.
>> Yeah, so I actually think more uh
C-level executives, they need to go into
the ring without the exoskeleton to to
actually experience this. I mean, I
think we've all been in meetings where
somebody are just super well prepared.
And you sit and you try to say something
relevant, but the other guy's just ahead
of you because he prepared.
This is the same thing, just 10x.
>> Mhm.
>> I love I love the metaphor you used. Um
I remember Steve Jobs saying famously
that computers are bicycles for the
mind.
And that was such a beautiful
expression of what computers truly were
as tools. And now we are all in this
bicycle race, right? We are all using
computers in this bicycle race. This
adds an engine to your bicycle, right?
You are now You are now motorbiking in a
bicycle race. Um
Here Here Here is what I what I what I'm
saying. Uh
Senior executives have hesitancy
because I think that there is a
combination of anxiety, a combination of
do we have the Do I have the time? And
if I'm not technology expert, if I'm not
really into that in that space, am I
going to be able to understand this? How
much How much time you need to dedicate
to this to follow this? There are many
And then of course there are there are I
think natural
a human reactions of fight or flight.
Like this is a This is a new and unusual
thing. Uh and some people are going to
naturally I think be inclined to lean in
and fight. And others are just going to
have a natural reaction of flight,
right? So, I think there are multiple
aspects to this. But to me,
as Daniel you pointed out,
probably the best way to take the team B
and make it team A is to ensure that
everyone in team B is exposed to how to
actually use a frontier model properly.
That's
That's starts the intellectual cascade.
It starts the intellectual avalanche if
you wish.
And it doesn't take long. And people
very soon realize that this is actually
much easier
than they thought.
That They don't need to be concerned
about which model is the leading model
at this particular moment this this
particular week.
And they can speak, you know, natural
language to it. So, people very quickly
learn,
and to me that's the cascade we want to
trigger and a fire we want to ignite.
>> By the way,
just a a small anecdote
from from European companies. I'm seeing
more and more saying, you know,
"We cannot
keep using US or Chinese tools. We we
need our own."
Which is probably the worst mistake that
they could make because, I mean, Europe
is so far behind in terms of frontier
models. They got this French one called
Mistral.
And if if you look at the benchmarks,
it's yeah, several years behind, I
guess.
Europe had the chance to to pivot in
terms of implementation if they really
wanted, but they can only do that with
frontier models. So, I think frontier
models are so important and and I I
pretty much
see, you know, I I think the space we
see right now is the space that's going
to lead this area in the next 10 years.
I don't see that we'll It's about
waiting for a new company or European
competitor. [clears throat] I think, you
know, OpenAI
Anthropic basically together with with
Google will definitely come back strong.
I'm I'm pretty sure. I think they will
lead the pack for for quite a number of
years.
>> For the foreseeable future, yeah. Yeah.
But it
We need to keep stressing this. The
right way to to approach this is to make
sure you have access and are using
frontier models.
And make sure that you you have a
structured and planned way to introduce
safe access to frontier models to your
company in your company with your and
and and orderly distributed to your
people top-down. This is really
important. This is where the
smartest things are happening, right?
That's what you want to access. And many
organizations for all the bunch of right
reasons,
uh
you know, don't yet have or don't yet
allow their leaders
uh authorized, proper, governed access
to frontier from within.
Uh
this
organizations needs to figure this out
quickly. We had a whole discussion on
our episode one
about shadow AI,
and most of the employees actually
already pe- people are learning and and
those who are not using this today might
start tomorrow.
Like, the overhang is very, very high
over us already.
So, in other words, as I said, don't you
can't really fight this. You need to
invite it orderly. That is your moment
to actually structurally approach,
method- methodically approach, and
introduce a frontier model access safely
to your company and start pouring
intelligence onto your people.
>> [laughter]
>> When I have seen uh executives or
leaders and and even middle management
and individual contributors,
there seems to be, you know, as Dalibor
said, you light the fire. Uh you know,
people go from fearful or anxious or
avoidant or dismissive or whatever, and
then there's an activation,
and there's the fire, and as I'm as I'm
reflecting on this, it usually comes
across as hunger,
uh aggression or competitiveness gets
activated in people. So, I'm curious if
you have any stories about that or or
how you get to that point uh with with
clients.
>> Yeah, so what I experienced uh in the
beginning is
uh
wh- when I talk to to the different
leaders uh across a company, I normally
kind of interview them and find out
their level in
in AI. And it's very clear, especially
in the US,
that they all feel they they have to
prove that they are
uh
relatively AI native or or or Sam uh
because
they feel the competition is already on
and not knowing how to use AI could
pretty much uh make you redundant or at
least behind kind of in the race with
with the peers. Um when you then come
down to it, uh most are still at a quite
uh basic level. So, I think it's it's
very important to just honestly map
where people actually are. And to be
honest, it doesn't matter that much
where they are. I think the once you
have experimented a little bit, just for
fun, uh basically, have probably uh gone
the longest
um because they have a you know, a feel
for what can AI do and what can AI not
do. But, it's definitely achievable for
for I think all of them to to catch up.
So, just being transparent and honest
about where you are is is key mapping in
in the early stages of working with a
>> Mhm. So, would you add that or would you
characterize that as just as by creating
an environment where you can be honest,
transparent, that creates that sense of
trust saying, "Hey, this is what I know,
this is what I don't know." And that
creates a more kind of inviting like
water's warm, come on in attitude.
>> Yeah, and then I think uh a lot of
people on stage, right? When they
present how far along their company is
with AI,
they exaggerate. And and there's nothing
new in that. And there was a lot of
exaggeration digital transformation as
well, right? So, I think just sitting
down, being honest, saying, "You know,
we are all still figuring this out." I
mean, the three of us, we also need to
be honest. We are all in the process of
figuring out the optimal solutions and
how to use AI the best way because we're
still so early in the development,
right? So, I think just, you know,
relaxing a little bit and say, you know,
how how do we take it from here? And,
you know,
if you hire some people who are just a
couple of of steps ahead of you and have
some frameworks, well, then you're
pretty much on the right path to
actually creating um
the processes with AI that will create
real return on investment for you.
>> Yeah.
Bang on. Excellent. Thinking out loud or
think thinking behind behind the scenes
for the next question.
Um we have between all of us
conducted some uh training at various
levels, um either receiving training,
giving training, uh whether it's
teaching frameworks or teaching hands-on
uh experience.
Uh my question has to do with what works
and what doesn't in that space.
Now, obviously, Dalibor, earlier you
mentioned um getting people just to show
them what the tool can do.
When I have done training courses, I
usually just I mean, one of my first
training courses, I was literally using
the tools to learn how to teach the
training course in real time. I was
solving my problem in real time. And I
thought that it was, you know, terrible,
but it was it was uh very well received
uh just because it people were seeing
the utility in that moment. And that was
Notebook LM, and that's actually how I
got as good at Notebook LM as as I am.
And for those in the audience that
aren't familiar with Notebook LM,
it allows you to uh upload many many
documents.
And then it applies Gemini directly to
those documents, and it allows you to
interact with them in many different
ways. You can generate tutorial videos,
you can generate reports, you can
generate podcasts, so it'll where you'll
have a two hosts that are kind of
discuss the material, generate slide
decks uh for you, which is really
interesting. Um so, that's just one
example of of uh I got good at a tool by
by virtue of teaching it. Now, not
everyone has that time or ability. So,
what have you guys seen out there that
works to really get people
um on board and to wrap their head
around uh some of these new tools,
whatever they happen to be?
>> Yeah.
So, I I I will start if you if you don't
mind um
>> Go ahead.
>> So, to me
um
there is no substitute for first-hand
experience, directly hands-on first-hand
experience
as we introduce people into the into
this domain.
So,
uh when I work with my clients in the
initial sessions, we are talking about
their priorities, their work, their
mandates, their domain, their industry,
their competition, their history, their
clients, the key opportunities, and so
on and so forth.
And I'm then helping them configure
their own private
you know, projects or a gem connected
with their you know, we're helping them
actually establish their own
their own tool to use on their real like
real-life examples, right?
So, step number one is is is making sure
that people are actually using it in a
context that is theirs to recognize so
that the value that they generate is not
just a training value, it's a real value
immediate.
Plus,
what I've learned is that there's almost
no point anymore in sending people to AI
training.
Things are moving so fast
that, you know, by the time a training
organization develops a training course,
approves the training course, stands up
the training course, sells the training
course, and starts the training course,
the train has left the station and moved
on. So, to me, what people need to do
and what I am doing actually to stay up
is is actually blatantly
straightforward.
You need to select YouTube channels,
Substack subscriptions, and follow daily
what's going on.
Be on X
with curiosity around AI.
Follow tectonic conversations, follow
critical path.
As a matter of fact, what I believe we
will be doing here in our regular
conversations is we are actually
providing
the ongoing training and learning and
without certification yet service to our
followers and people who watch this. So,
if you if you follow us over time,
you're going to be up-to-date with
what's going on in corporate use of AI
and automation and what are the key
topics and of discussions and maybe this
will help you teach you and help you
accelerate how you do it, your
transformation in your company. So, to
me then to wrap this back,
I don't think that it's really valuable
to consider AI training for everybody.
Let's send people to AI training. I
think the real value right now is to
make sure people have hands-on
first-hand experience safely coached
plus
ongoing access to ongoing training
because the industry is moving that
fast.
>> Yeah, I think uh one thing that has
helped me
um
uh help clients with this is to take a
personal example. For example, um
I didn't want I didn't know where to
move next in the world. For people who
know me, I've lived in several different
countries and now we want to try
something new. Um so, I built an AI
model to help me decide where I should
live in the world. So, it interviewed me
first then it interviewed my wife, my
two kids. And uh we had for example some
non-starters like we wanted to do
homeschooling so it had to be in a
country where that was allowed.
And we hate the rain and the cold so we
could not choose a place in the world
where where it was too rainy or cold.
And so, we had like a bunch of things
that would be like positives or
negatives, right? Um
then after it kind of copied our brains
and put put into a model,
uh I did a lot of deep research on uh um
20 countries. Uh so, simply having
ChatGPT working overtime with these deep
research reports, putting that into the
model, and then it kind of spat out,
"Well, I see you thriving in six places
in the world, including uh three states
in in the US, uh which is what we ended
up deciding." And when when people see
that model, they're like,
"Wow, this is interesting, right?" And
it makes sense because choosing where to
live is such a major decision, right?
And once they see that, they start
thinking, "Okay, what major decisions do
I take in the company? Where it would
would be great to build this mentor,
this brain, this library of research to
help me make the right decision." And
this could be huge negotiations for for
millions and millions of dollars, sales
pitches, uh entries into new markets.
Uh once people see this, they get ideas,
and then they get working, and then they
they also then see their shortcomings,
like, "How do I actually build this?"
And and I think that's a wonderful way
to start.
>> Yeah.
>> That's how we ignite the fire, exactly.
>> Yeah. Even even what we're doing here on
Critical Path was the result of
conversations between humans, but then
also feeding those transcripts into
ChatGPT and saying, "Okay,
look us up, you know, this is what we
do, and help me figure out a business
model." And you know, that's
that's what we're doing. So, um
next question is,
"What beliefs don't work that we have
seen out there uh in in the real world?
What beliefs are problematic or
stumbling blocks
uh that clients have expressed?" Or or
if not clients, then leaders inside
inside companies.
>> I I think any type of fear of working
against technology. I mean,
historically, that has never really
worked, right? I think we all remember
when the the first smartphone came out
out of 100 people in the workplace,
there were always
the 10 of 10 people saying, "I will
reject the smartphone." Right?
And
I I think we're seeing the same thing
with AI.
Um
unfortunately, uh
and and that simply doesn't work.
I mean, it's pretty much you're labeling
yourself a dinosaur, and we all know
what happens uh to to the dinosaurs.
Um so, yeah, I think that's the number
one. Curiosity is good.
Um
you know, trial and error is great,
iteration is great, strategy is even
better in terms of AI, but but fear and
rejection
are um
path to to failure, definitely.
>> I think there is a
palatable
uh you know,
concern about job security and
disruption, and that that is causing a
lot of people
to
see it as a real threat, and therefore
reject it fundamentally
as something that they want to avoid or
postpone.
And
I completely actually understand that. I
completely understand that sentiment.
And as I said, this is I believe this is
at the very core part of our
evolutionary reaction to an unknown
threat, and we can either fight or
flight.
And I think those that can be
a part of the maybe explanation of why
some people
naturally are are very concerned and
reject it.
The challenge that I see with that is
that, unlike, you know, I like in the
savanna
5 million years ago,
I don't think there is anywhere to hide
from this particular lion.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? So, while of course we still of
course have thriving communities who
reject electricity
and they live successfully today, right?
That is not how the rest of
civilization is operating. And I think
that's what what what is going to repeat
here,
but at a dramatically accelerated
timeline in a much more impactful way.
So, the people who choose to not
participate
um
may find themselves at a notable
disadvantage soon, right? So, my advice
to everybody is you know, just without
judgment of if it is good or bad, what
it is, it's neutral. It it is what you
make of it, and it will ultimately
amplify all of us,
which actually gives me hope. I am an
optimist.
There is no other way than to to
gradually, safely, slowly engage.
>> Yeah, maybe I can add to that. I think
it's important to be candid. I mean,
everyone will not be winners. It's it's
like that in every technology, right?
And and I think that the challenge comes
when you look at company structures.
There are some very smart people who are
maybe in the late stages of their
career,
and their best bet might actually be
delaying the AI project because that
could prolong their their own career and
their own relevance, right? And this is
where I think leadership becomes so
important that you acknowledge that, you
respect it, you accept it, but then you
have a conversation saying, you know, we
as a company can unfortunately not live
with the obstruction. So, you know,
let's find a a
a solution that that will work for for
all parties. And and when I say that, I
mean work for all parties. I mean, it
does not mean that these people need to
be demoted in any way. It it can be that
some of their abilities and skills and
knowledge can be reapplied in in a way
that is even more valuable than before
and that that they might even enjoy
more than before.
I think a big problem is the elephant in
the room, right? I think we all know the
companies where where the C-suite are
nervous. They are anticipating
what is next and will I survive the next
wave of technology or change. And I
think it's we need to be head-on here
and say, "Well, this is what the next
wave looks like."
Most people can add value in in some
aspect, right? So, let's find out where
we fit in the new puzzle.
>> 100%.
>> And think of it if you have if you're
listening to this and experiencing this,
my invitation is
think of this as you now have ability to
add to your IQ by plugging into into a
wall literally for
for for a price that's almost free to
meter.
You can ask it to help you think through
this, actually.
You know? So,
it Daniel, thank you for that comment.
Really right on.
Again, my my my reaction would be even
even further reason
to you know, to try this out and and and
and see to what degree it can be
helpful.
>> What are some of the worst things that
senior leadership can do at this time or
juncture
with respect to onboarding generative AI
or getting their own heads around
generative AI or getting adoption
kickstarted in their organization?
>> I think delegation is is the worst thing
they can do, right?
And it is what they most of them are
doing, right? They are thinking, "This
is not something that should be on my
table. I'm I'm super busy. I'll find
somebody technical to delegate to." So,
what we're often seeing is CEO delegates
to the CFO because they think it's a
cost-cutting exercise,
who then works with technology, and then
they find a couple of champions in their
departments who does not have
the strategic overview of the company to
to make a real change, right? So, I
think
the CEO and the C-suite, they need to
amplify themselves. This does not mean
that they need to become nerds or AI
experts.
They simply need to start applying it in
a strategic way and have AI help them
lead the AI transformation of the
>> Yes. And another bad thing that that
we've seen organizations do is
lean it lean into it
too quickly
cascading it to people without help and
direction and then realizing that
suddenly we have very high costs and
very little value, which completely
deflates the whole point of this and
takes it into a
wrong trajectory.
So,
I think that orga- in addition to what
what Daniel you said, I I think
organizations to be very clear about
what are the incentives they're going to
put in place.
Uh
who is going to be accountable
to to actually provide value.
Um so, leaning into this too fast again
could be could be equally as bad
as trying to stop it and prevent it.
Perhaps that's another
reaction that I that I disagree with.
You know, stopping usage.
Just blocking it. I think that's that's
um
I think that's a that's a wrong
approach. I think we need
There has to be a consideration of how
do we
operate within
and not try to stay out.
>> We already know some of the things that
that AI are doing in organizations and
and and we know them from from watching
companies such as Google and and that's
a
plan and for example. So, we we are
seeing that middle managers will be
pressured because they have a lot of
delegation that will not be be needed.
We are seeing that the most junior roles
they will not really be hired for
because AI can do it. And again, I think
we need quite early to address, you
know, what are we going to do about
this? What are we going to do with
middle managers? Which middle managers
will will become individual contributors
at a higher level and and how can we
facilitate other middle managers have
the capability to become very strategic
and becoming become top managers? Um
and how do we let junior people with the
right personal skills
into the organization, but teach them to
to create value? I mean, it could be
that we we need a new system of
positions without salaries for the first
year because you cannot add value um
because basically you will be doing AI's
work and and you will simply need to
learn to understand how the company
works. So, there are some new structures
that we have not yet put in place that
we need to discuss and I think each
company needs to address these issues
and say, "Yes, it is true. We will need
fewer middle managers. Here are the path
uh that we are working on
and we need to talk to you individually
to find out what your future look like."
>> When should an organization
bring in new blood and who should they
look for?
>> I think first they need to map like
what do we want to achieve? Then what
organization could achieve that?
And how can we up-level the people we
have?
And then look at the gaps, right? What
do we what do we need that we don't
currently have? And
um where we cannot kind of pivot people
to to grow into these roles.
>> I would say that the most important
skill sets that I would be looking for
from junior people
is no longer necessarily their
knowledge.
Uh
it's their communication skill,
curiosity,
resilience. To me, those are the three
that's the three I think power
you know,
power corners of the triangle, right?
Those are the people that can navigate
an organization, that can learn, that
can adopt, that can um
and that can sustain performance over
periods of uncertainty and successfully
come out on the other end.
So,
I think that's really the skill that
I would advise young people to practice
and learn and use, you know, higher
education institutions
as opportunities to to practice
human-to-human relationships and those
communication skills more than as a you
know, institution that's going to teach
you how to what you need to know to
succeed in your career. I think that
ship has sailed.
>> I think that's a great point and I also
think at an individual level you can
look at yourself and say, "How do I
currently contribute and add value to
the company?" Right? So, some people are
great at delegation. That will
disappear. Some people are like an
you know, have a huge amount of
knowledge about the company and the
industry, a lot of that will kind of be
substituted by AI as well, right?
But but some people, like they have uh
great communication skills, inter-human
uh skills, great at solving conflicts,
uh very strategic, very creative, and so
on, which will probably be more
important skills in the coming years,
right? So, again, this is not static,
right? You can say, "Okay, but how am I
adding value in places that AI will take
over?" So, I need to strengthen, you
know, my value add in the areas where AI
will not add so much.
>> Keep Imagine if if any everyone in the
organization
clearly knew what are their strengths.
And then if they are an exceptional
engineer,
how do I use AI around me to be a super
engineer, an amplified engineer? If my
thing is interpersonal skills, how do I
become the magnet of the people? How do
I become like How do we use
Challenge yourself by saying, "How do I
use AI around me to completely amplify
my strengths and make that
an anchor of my value proposition in the
organization that I'm in, and how do I
approve every day, but at the same time,
how do you help me work on whatever the
gaps might Like that's how I will be
thinking of this, right? And imagine an
organization that that where every
leader has done that, and they bring
every day their amplified selves.
>> Imagine that we produce data all the
time, right? Like for example, just
doing this podcast, right? I will take
the transcript of this and put it into
my personal model, right? And and then
it will score my behavior, saying,
"You're interrupting too much. You're
talking too much." Or or whatever I'm
doing wrong, and it will tell me in a
nice way not to hurt my feelings too
much how I can do better next time. Um
and I think we we forget that we produce
this
huge amount of data that we can put to
good use to improve ourselves all the
time.
>> What does AI native mean in today in
today's age in respect to generative AI,
and is it important for leaders and
executives to understand?
>> I think nobody knows the answer. So, I
hope you won't know the answer then.
>> [laughter]
>> But no, I would say I think we all
define it
differently, right? For me, AI native is
when you have a problem, you consider
how can AI help you solve this problem,
and and then you use AI as part of the
process. That's AI native for me. It's
not about if you can
build custom GPTs or whether you can
automate a ton of functions. Uh that
might for some people be AI native. For
leaders, I think it's about
problem-solving. How AI will help you
make better decisions and build a
stronger strategy.
>> I I have a like something dawned on me,
a bit of a philosophical response, if
you don't mind me.
>> Go for it.
>> You said, "What is AI native?"
To me,
and I think I'm kind of getting there.
I no longer want to refer to this thing
as artificial intelligence
because in my experience, I use this
daily 4 or 6 hours every day for work.
Like this is how I run my business.
I'm I don't think there's anything
really artificial
in this intelligence.
It is a digital intelligence. It's a
different form of intelligence, but it
is intelligence.
So, to me,
being in artificial AI native
equates to being intelligence agnostic
as in
we recognize that there is biological
biological intelligence. This is who we
are and what we do. And now we have a
mechanical intelligence.
It's not artificial, it's real, but it's
mechanical. It's real, but it's digital.
And
I now think of me as someone who has
ability to tap into different
forms of intelligences and combine them
together for the most impactful results.
That ultimately helps me lead a better
life myself and make impact
to, you know, with my friends, to the
rest of us, I guess.
>> [clears throat]
>> And to close out, let's do our
final uh
ritual, which is what is what is the big
big thing that you have learned or the
big pro tip that you can share.
Uh and it can be personal, it can be
something um professional, whatever it
happens to be.
And what I will say is uh I'm I'm going
to I'm going to piggyback off something
that Daniel said earlier, which is
really see how much you can use AI to
make big decisions. Uh you know, he made
he he he used the example of using AI to
help decide where to live. And I used AI
to help form a business plan. And not
just a, you know, generic ask ChatGPT to
form a business plan for me, but it was
a conversation to say, "This is where
I'm at. This is the team. This is what I
think is next. Let's consolidate around
that." And that became a nucleus, and
it's interesting because you can zoom in
to every single step of any single
process.
And that zooming in is usually where the
real value lives in in my experience.
So, uh Daniel or or Dalibor, either guy
who wants to go first, what's your
what's your big big aha moment, your
your your
to share with the world about
to maximize AI value
this week. So,
>> given that this episode was about
fluency and and sort of AI leadership
and top-down, here is what it here is my
comment on that.
You you don't have to at all be
tech-savvy, tech-literate executive
to start benefiting from this
tomorrow.
Uh
open invitation is
sign up and and and cross the bridge
um
today rather than tomorrow.
>> There you go. Daniel?
>> Yeah, I think it's always ask the bigger
question first to AI.
Um so, what I mean by that is if if you
own a company, right? Instead of saying,
you know, I you know, instead of giving
AI a task first saying, I think we
should make an AI strategy. Can you help
me with that? Say, instead,
"What do you think I should do with my
company for the next 5 years? You know,
and what would you need to know for me
to help me make that decision?"
And once you've gone through all these
steps, which is extremely healthy, I
mean, it could even be on a personal
level you would say,
"How do I become the happiest person
possible, right?"
Later it might say, "Okay, you love
money and you love your family, so
spend more time with your family and
make more money and here's how you do
that."
But if you don't start with the bigger
question, you may actually get the
answer to the wrong question.
>> Mhm.
Love that. Ask the right questions and
think bigger. That is that is a through
line for today's episode. Well,
gentlemen, thank you as always for being
with me on the critical path and we will
We'll everyone next week on the Critical
Path. Have a good one. Bye-bye. All
right. And Dalibor, you've got